<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain considerations: being the legitimate issue of a true English heart: presented to the free-holders, and to the free men of the several corporations in this nation; to regulate their elections of Members to serve in the next Parliament, to be holden the 25. of Aprill, 1660.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E765_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E765[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain considerations: being the legitimate issue of a true English heart: presented to the free-holders, and to the free men of the several corporations in this nation; to regulate their elections of Members to serve in the next Parliament, to be holden the 25. of Aprill, 1660.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 26.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Elections --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118482:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN CONSIDERATIONS: BEING The LEGITIMATE ISSUE OF <hi>A True</hi> ENGLISH <hi>Heart:</hi> Preſented to the <hi>Free-holders,</hi> and to the <hi>Free Men</hi> of the ſeveral <hi>Corporations</hi> in this NATION; To Regulate their ELECTIONS OF MEMBERS to Serve in the next PARLIAMENT, To be holden the 25. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1660. <add>March. 26.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118482:2"/>
            <head>Certain Conſiderations, being the Legitimate Iſſue of a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> heart; Preſented to the Free-holders, and to the Free-men of the ſeveral Corporations in this Nation, to regulate their Elections of Members to ſerve in the next <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> to be holden the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>Aprill, 1660.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>TAcitus</hi> makes it the bane of the Ancient <hi>Britains, Quod in Commune non Conſulunt,</hi> That is, they had no Common-Councels, by which that great Statiſt meant either, Parliaments, or ſomething equivalent to them: And certainly Parliaments are the beſt Phyſick of a ſick State, but when the Phyſick ſhall become the diſeaſe, and by Factions, Intereſt, Atheiſme, and the Conſequents of that (Sacriledge and contempt of that juſt Authority) ſhall make the Nation ſick of its own Remedy, and turn bleſſings themſelves into curſes, the wound both of Church and State, will grow ſo wide, that none butan Almighty hand can cloſe them.</p>
            <p>And thus hath this poor diſtracted Nation (been near 20 years) ſick of their Phyſicians, and now lies almoſt at the laſt gaſp, with bleeding hearts, and watery eyes; we cannot but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, (for it is a Miſery to remember how happy we were) that the laſt late King <hi>Charles,</hi> (the beſt of Princes, the Peoples Martyr, and his Martyrdome the Aſtoniſhment and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake of all Princes in the world) in the 16 year of his Reign did ſummon a Parliament, to be holden at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on the 2. of <hi>November</hi> in the ſame year; to conſult with the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and other great men of the Kingdome, concerning the difficult, and urgent Affairs of the King and State, and of the defence of the Kingdome and Church of <hi>England,</hi> (then glorious to the envie of ſome other States, and the Admiration of all.) To this Parliament (according to the ſummons) came the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, of the ſeveral Counties, Cities and Burroughs, elected by the vertue of the ſaid Writ, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> ever ſince the 9. year of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. And this was the firſt time that the Commons were admitted Members of Parliament, and to fit in a diſtinct Houſe by themſelves; but let this Truth never be forgotten, that they ſate then but in the Nature of a Grand Jury, to preſent the grievances and deſires of the people, and on their behalf to conſent to ſuch Lawes as ſhould be there ordained: but that Houſe of Commons taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage either by the weakneſs, or neceſſities of their ſucceeding Kings, grew as we have ſeen to ſuch an exorbitancie of Power, till at laſt they gave Law to their Maſters, and made the King himſelf but a Royal Homager.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, the Parliament conſiſting (as it ought) of Lords and Commons, met ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly in their reſpective Houſes, and (according to cuſtome) did ſeverally take the Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacie, whereby they ſwore, (O remember this all ye that did ſwear) [To bear true Faith to the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs, and Succeſſors, and to defend him and them, againſt all attempts and conſpiracies againſt them, their Perſons, Crown and Dignity, and they did ſwear that they did abhor that damnable doctrine, (and a damnable one it is) That Princes might be murthered and depoſed, this they ſwore:] But did they keep this Oath when they made their Iniquitie to triumph, and erected the Scaffold, the ſad and unexpected Scean of the late Kings Death, upon the very Margin of his Throne, and made him goe out of the world at his own Door? Poor <hi>Cateline,</hi> whoſe modeſt Crimes made <hi>Tully</hi> eloquent enough to make his Crimes greater by his Eloquence; but here <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf would have been bankrupt, and amaſement become the beſt Rhetorick.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118482:3"/>
            <p> The Parliament thus met the King in a Speech, declares his willing and ready concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to cure all the grievances of his People, and to enact ſuch Laws as ſhould tend in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it: And becauſe the Court of <hi>Star-chamber, High Commiſſion,</hi> and <hi>Councel Table,</hi> were great eye-ſores to ſome men, (who liked no power which might control their diſregard of Laws and juſt Authority,) His Majeſty graciouſly conſented to aboliſh the two firſt, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the laſt; And more then this, deveſted himſelf of all Power, giving away the <hi>Militia</hi> both by Sea and Land, to thoſe who wanted his Power to deſtroy him, and ſecure their crimes? Tonnage and Poundage were laid at the feet and pleaſure of the Parliament, and Monopoliſts and other Delinquents left to Juſtice, and the grant of a Triennial Parliament was made the Monument of the Kings Goodneſs, and the means to the peoples perpetual felicity: And might we not ſtop here, and ſay, Happy are the people that be in ſuch a caſe! The people had (now) nothing to ask, nor the King to give, that reaſon could require; but this could not ſatisfie men, who ſcorn'd the Throne, and were reſolved that their Ambition ſhould trample upon the very Goodneſs of their King: And therefore now Religion and Reformation (The uſual Maſque of Rebellion) muſt be the Engine to earch the people, whoſe power they wanted to oppreſs their King: and the publique Faith muſt be pawn'd to raiſe Money to gratifie our <hi>(Dear Scottiſh Brethren)</hi> who muſt needs be ſent for, and an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of 20000. invi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to force the people to a New Religion, (for the Old was condemn'd, without the Liberty of ſpeaking for it ſelf. But the moſt of this Deſign was but in projection as yet: ſuch an <hi>Embrio</hi> could not be produced, without the grant of a <hi>perpetual Parliament,</hi> which (by the Kings Neceſſities) they ſoon wreſted from him. Now <hi>was the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance forgot,</hi> and the King affronted with all the effects of hold defiance, and the ſix Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers accuſed of Treaſon by their Prince, and in due courſe of Law impeached in the Houſe of Peers protected, and the King traduced with the breach of their priviledges, and yet till then, never any Member claimed priviledge for Felony or Treaſon: Of which laſt, had thoſe Gentlemen been free, the world could not have given them ſo much Honour, as would have grown to them by their Trial. The Innocent never dread the Tribunal, the guilty only fear; Yet the Members juſtifie themſelves, but it is with the numbers of the people, and by force and affronts about the Royal Pallace, endanger the King to their fury, who now deveſted of of all Power, (but that of an unconquered Patience) makes an Honourable flight to <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore,</hi> to give his afflictions breath, and to conſider the ſafety of his Royal Conſort and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Children: The Queen leaves the Land, becauſe ſhe could not be ſafe in it; and the King, (as far as he had any Land) accompanies her. The King finding the <hi>South</hi> ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous ſeeks a Calm in the <hi>North;</hi> but that the Storm may meet him there too Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> the Fatal Father of as Fatal a Son, is ſent with 500. Souldiers to keep <hi>Hull</hi> for them who there denied the King a peaceable Entrance into his own Town: And now a Vote paſſeth to raiſe 10000. men upon pretence to defend the Parliament againſt the King, who was ſo far from having a Camp, that his numbers ſcarcely exceeded a Court, nor was there about him any <hi>Militiarie</hi> appearance as yet: and the Complexion of his Meſſage of the 20. of <hi>January,</hi> 1641. Courting them to peace, with the offers of more Acts of Grace then could modeſtly be expected from the moſt indulgent Prince) is a ſufficient Demonſtration, how little he delighted in his peoples blood, or his own revenge: But this Meſſage, (though the King often preſt for an Anſwer of it) had none, but what a Battail fought againſt his very Perſon at <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> ſpoke in the Language of the Cannon, (for by that time their contempt and ſpeedy marching toward him, had ſummond him, to receive ſuch perſons as would hazard their Lives and Fortunes for their Princes preſervation.</p>
            <p>Now was the whole Kingdome in a jealous trepidation, A war was begun, and the Citty of <hi>London</hi> doubtful of the Effects of ſuch ſad and unnatural Hoſtility, Petition for Peace, but (with others of the ſame Inclination and Addreſs) were oppoſed by the Souldiery (incour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged for that purpoſe) and beaten and wounded, and trodden under the feet of the Horſe-Troups, where (in the Pallace yard) ſome ſeeking peace loſt their lives.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118482:3"/>
            <p> And as the Kings Meſſages of Peace (ſo often repeated) were ever ſleighted, ſo his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers for Peace were uſed, and one carried to <hi>London</hi> blind-folded through their quarters was thence impriſon'd, and after many weeks confinement at laſt, return'd without the leaſt word of anſwer; They blinded his eyes who came for the Nations Peace, becauſe they ſaw not the things which belong'd to their own. For <hi>Colbrook,</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> are witneſſes of the Kings endeavour for Peace, and how unſucceſsful all his Treaties were, which could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver procure ſo much as a Ceſſation of Arms. And after all this, he offer'd his Sacred Perſon among them, (an attempt o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no ſmal hazard, yet diſcovering abundantly how much he thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted after his peoples Happineſs) that ſo his Treaties of Peace might be more proſperous, but could not be admitted, with how little Variation might we ſay, He would have come to his own, but they would not receive him.</p>
            <p>But next, let the pretended Cauſes of the War be conſidered, and they (as their <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1642. told us) was firſt to defend the true Proteſtant Religion; and this they defended, by purſuing, and at laſt deſtroying them who were the Defenders of it: The Pillars of the Church, the reverend Biſhops, and moſt of the reverend Divines of the Nation (for the defence of Religion) were-ſuppreſſed, and their Freeholds (for ſo were their Benefices) raviſh'd from them, they, their Wives and Children turnd out of dores, to ſeek their Meat in deſolate places; and to their Places were preferr'd ſome of <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s bleating Calves, to bellow out their <hi>Cauſe</hi> among the People, who had not abſolutely (as yet) ſhook hands with Loyalty: And now a race of dumb Aſſes are raiſed up, to forbid the p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etended Madneſs of the Prophets, and an inundation of Sectaries ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ruſh in and overwhelm the Religion theſe good States men pretended to defend; and the greateſt Atheiſts made the Darlings of the Times, whileſt the Children of this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who durſt ſacrifice to their God (according to the Diſcipline and Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) were puniſh'd and impriſon'd: And to defend Religion the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the <hi>Birth-day</hi> of our Saviour (to gratifie their Brethren the <hi>Jews</hi>) was profaned, and the Obſervation thereof made a Crime.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they declared to defend the Kings perſon, whileſt their <hi>Pulpits</hi> and their <hi>Preſſes</hi> (and that without control) ſpoke noth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng but Treaſon and Rebell<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on: They defended him with Volleys of undiſtinguiſhing Shot, Pikes and Canon; and when forc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d from place to place, ſeeking ſecurity, and finding none, he had thought to make the <hi>Scots</hi> his refuge, this rock daſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d him in peices, and they (the <hi>Scots</hi>) his own Natural Subjects) ſold him to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who (more generouſly wicked than the <hi>Jews</hi>) gave 1000000 <hi>l.</hi> for him; a great price, yet leſs than he was worth; but that vaſt ſumme was made the price of Blood, and a Counterfeit high Court (I cannot ſay of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> though they called it ſo) Arraigned, Condemned, and Murther'd their <hi>King,</hi> not without the prefaces of many grand indignities, and ſpitting in his face: His erected <hi>Statua</hi> which honored the <hi>Exchange,</hi> thrown down, and an Infamous Inſcription (calling him <hi>Tyr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) for they perſecuted him after his Death) became the Monument of their Inſolence and Rebellion; and when they had kill'd the Heir, they ſeiſed on his Inheritance, ſelling and ſharing his Eſtate among them.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, let it be conſidered, how well the <hi>Priviledges of Parliament</hi> (ſo much declared for) were defended) when by the help of their Janizaries, they ſecluded a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of their own Members at a time, and impriſoned above forty more, for no other known Crime, but that they were wearie of their owne Crimes, and through horror of Conſcience thought not fit to oppreſs their King any more: And that theſe mens Ambition might reign alone, the Houſe of Peers (the undoubted Birth-right of the Nobility) was diſſolved by a Vote, and no footſteps of Nobility were to be found in <hi>Parliament,</hi> but that the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (to honor the Peers Houſe and his owne) in great humility availed his goodneſs (defying as much the checks of his <hi>Blew Garter,</hi> as thoſe of his <hi>Conſcience</hi>) was preferred into a Burgeſs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118482:4"/>
            <p> And fourthly, let it be conſidered, how well the liberty and rights of the Subject have been defended by theſe grand Declarers for their Defence, and that will appear by their inforced Loans, Contributions, Parting Mens Eſtates, taking the <hi>fifth</hi> and <hi>twentieth</hi> part, and by that diſhonorable way of Exciſe; and for the better enjoyment of the Subjects Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betties, laying them in priſon, and forbidding the Benefit of a <hi>Habeas Corpus:</hi> And have not the Laws been trampled under foot, and <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> made the ſport and ſcorn of <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Ambition, who muſt be made <hi>Protector,</hi> that ſo the Guilty might not want protection, nor the Innocent to be oppreſs'd? And here let it be conſidered, Whether the Kings <hi>Proclamation</hi> of the 24. of <hi>October,</hi> 1642. were not Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical, when he told them, their War was to take away his Life, to Deſtroy his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to Change the Religion, to ſuppreſs the Laws, and to make the People Miſerable by an Arbitrary power? And are there not (as Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s <hi>Memento</hi> tells us) above one hundred <hi>Declarations, Remonſtrances, Petitions,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of their owne, to witneſs their <hi>Perjuries</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let it be conſidered, Whether the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> (that holy Engine of Diviſion) will not, as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſpeaks, ſtare in their faces, and engage God and the three Kingdoms againſt them if they ſhould proceed (as ſince they have done) to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the King, and Diſinherit his Poſterity?</p>
            <p>Oh! Conſider then, whether theſe men be ever to be truſted with Power, or to ſit within thoſe Walls again? Meddle not with them that have been given to ſuch Changes as have Crumbled the Nation into ſo many Parties and Factions: Are they not guilty of the greateſt Perjuries, of the greateſt Murther (ſince that of our <hi>Saviour</hi>) that ever aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd the world: Wherefore was it that the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> before his Death declin'd them? Wherefore was it that the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> Coll. <hi>Popham,</hi> and many others of great note, quitted their Stations, and by that, teſtified enough, how much they abominated theſe Impicties in their fellow Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, And yet how ready were theſe men (in the late little pretended Parliament called the RUMP) to make the Nation drink deeper of their Tyranny, had not his Excellency the preſent Lord General clipt the wings of their Pride and Ambition, by over ballancing them with a return of the formerly oppreſſed and ſecluded Members? And though they be now diſſolved (though againſt their wills) yet being moſt unwearied, and Induſtrious perſuers of their former evil deſigns, they are earneſtly at work in all Counties, uſing all means, (in which their friends and Partiſans, the Anabaptiſts, Quakers, and other Sectaries are the inſtruments) to procure themſelves to be elected again to ſerve in the next Parliament. And ſhould you (Dear Brethren) be ſwayed to ſuch elections (after ſuch a miſerable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the Nation hath had of them) you would make the laſt error worſe then the firſt, and by ſuch elections (Juſtifying what they have done) you would give them the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to make your ſelves more miſerable; and then they had your own conſent, to juſtifie your undoing.</p>
            <p>Conſider how much the Church and State flouriſh'd before theſe Men rooted up the foundations of both; Conſider how long the Nation hath groaned under their oppreſſions: Conſider how they would perpetuate their Uſurpation and our Thraldom, by endevouring to entail their power upon their Poſterities, that ſo within a generation or two, Tyrany might be natural to them, and ſlavery to us: Conſider whether theſe Men have made the Nation rich, or themſelves? Conſider whether theſe Sacrilegious Men, who have got the Revenews of the Church into their hands, are ever likely to advance Religion, or that thoſe who have uſed their Prince ſo ill, can love the people? Conſider that there is but one way under heaven to make the Nation happy, and that the guilt of theſe Men is ſo great, that they had rather drown the Nation in its own blood, and make your lives the Bulworks to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their own, then conſent to it, for great Guilt is ever ſuſpitious, and hardly made to believe it is pardoned, though it be ſo: And now the ſpare is broken by their diſſolution, let not your own hands weave nets to entangle you, but by your Elections ſhew you are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118482:4"/>willing to be redeemed, ſhould you put theſe Men in power again, your now bleeding Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion would give up the ghoſt, your Laws (thoſe great diſtinguiſhers betwixt right and wrong) would hang at the point of their ſwords, your Eſtates would be no more, then they would ſpare you from thoſe Multiplied Neceſſities which their Ambition and guilt will ſtill Create; Conſider that in the Elections, you do Conſign over all theſe (and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is dear unto you) to the truſt of thoſe you do elect, Truſt not thoſe who have ſo oft deceived you, and believe it, it concerns you next to the Eternal State of your Souls, to make a prudent Election; And do not ſuffer your ſelves to be cheared into an opinion of a Free Parliament, when you have no ſuch thing; And conſider that theſe Men took care before they diſſolved, to ſhuffle in ſuch reſtrictions and Qualifications, as ſhould almoſt ſhut out all Men from being Elected but themſelves; And conſider, that theſe Men had no power to impoſe ſuch Qualifications upon you, and you will be but too forward to Seal to your own Miſchiefs, if you obſerve them; And conſider beſides, that the hatred of theſe Men to the KING, lives ſtill (though he be dead) in their hatred to thoſe, who (out of Conſcience of their duty) hazzarded themſelves in defence of his juſt Cauſe; For thoſe Qüalifications tell us, that not onely no perſon who hath been in Arms for the KING ſhall be elected, but that their Sons ſhall not be Capeable of being elected, and yet ſome of thoſe Sons were not eight years old, and poſſibly ſome unborn: Theſe great pretenders to Religion, love not to immitate God, <hi>in ſhewing Mercy unto thouſands,</hi> but yet can <hi>viſit the Iniquity of the fathers upon the Children,</hi> and perhaps (if ever they have power again) <hi>to</hi> more then <hi>the third and fourth Generation:</hi> by which they have broke all the engagements of honour, as they have done thoſe of <hi>Allegiance:</hi> for by the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> (at the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render thereof) and by the <hi>Articles</hi> of other Garriſons it was agreed that all Compriſed in thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> ſhould enjoy all the priviledges and Immunities of other ſubjects; and yet a lawful Election may preferre their Innocent Sons to a forfeiture of a 1000 <hi>l.</hi> for daring to ſerve their Country: No Civil war (not that of the Barons) did ever yet abridge the people of their Electing Liberties, but this Act was Contrived, that under the pretence of a Free Parliament, they might be free onely to chooſe them, who have already offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Noſtrils of God and Man; and for that ill ſavour, as well as for that they were but the remaining part of a Parliament, they have been called the <hi>Rump:</hi> but let the people take heed, for ſhould theſe <hi>Rumpers</hi> appear in Parliament again, like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes they would turn tail to tail, and between every two tails you ſhall be ſure to have ſuch a fire brand, as would kindle new Combuſtions, they having no way of ſafety but the Nations general danger.</p>
            <p>All this conſidered, deareſt Countrey men, ſtand fix'd to aſſert your Freedoms, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be out-numbred, and ſhould not (therefore) be out-vallor'd, and I hope you will not be outvapored: By the ſelf denying Ordinance of the third of <hi>April,</hi> 1645 never to be repealed (though never yet obſerved by thoſe who made it) it was ordained that no officer whether Militarie or Civil, ſhould be a <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the ſword will Create occaſions to exerciſe it ſelf, for by that Craft they get their living: And let not the Importment of <hi>Barebones</hi> Petition be forgot (which was ſo authenticated by the Speakers ſollemn thanks) and that Petition moved the abjuration of King <hi>James</hi> his line by Act of Parliament, and that a Motion for a Single Perſon, as alſo the Motion to revoke that Law (when enacted) ſhould be High Treaſon, and the thanks of the Houſe ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately beſtowed upon <hi>Barebone,</hi> ſhews what priviledges they would leave to ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Parliaments, when the Laws of this muſt be unalterable, of this did I ſay, I muſt recant that, for they were none, the KINGS death, the ſeveral Interruptions, <hi>the Change</hi> of Government with ſeveral intermediate Parliaments makes them none: And yet they have taken upon them to iſſue Writs in the Name of <hi>the (Inviſible Keepers of the Liberties of England)</hi> ſummoning a new Parliament, which notwithſtanding by the prudence of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors in the fit choyce of perſons) may heal all thoſe wounds of which the Nation hath ſo long Complained: And they cannot manifeſt that prudence better then in ſteering the Elections by theſe rules;</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118482:5"/>
            <p> Firſt, that they chooſe no purchaſer of any of the Lands of the late KING, nor of the Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters, nor of any Lands (pretendedly) forfeited for delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That they chooſe none who have gained Offices, or made any Advantage by the late troubles.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That they chooſe none who have been or are, Commanders in the former or preſent Armies.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That they chooſe no perſon who hath been, or is, a Commiſſioner for Exciſe, Monethly Taxes, or any other burthens of the people.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, That waving all Conſideration of the new pretended Qualifications (as Engliſh Men) they ſteer by the Laws, which (in ſhort) direct the Electors thus: That the Knights to be choſen ſhall be notable Knights of the ſame Shire,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat.</hi> 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 15. <hi>Stat.</hi> 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. <hi>Stat.</hi> 8. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. <hi>Stat.</hi> 10. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. <hi>Stat.</hi> 23. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 14.</note> or elſe ſome notable Eſquire, or Gentlemen born, of the ſame County, and that no Yeoman or Perſon inferior ſhall be choſen: And that the Electors, and Knights elected muſt be ſuch as were reſident in the County, for which they ſerve, on the day of the date of the Writs, and that Citizens and Burgeſſes be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in, and free of the Cities and Burroughs, for which they ſerve, And the puniſhment of a Sheriff making a falſe return, or of a Maior, or Bailiff ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, would be Conſidered alſo, and may be found in the Statutes cited in the Margin. And now (Dear Country Men) you have (as I may ſay) Life and Death before you, Good and Evil, Happineſs and Mifery, chooſe Life, and Good, and Happineſs: Make the Children yet unborn, to praiſe God for you, Let your Management of this Election be the Monument of your love to your Country: Make up your breaches, Redeem the Captived Nation, by ſuch a choyce, as may heal all our Diſtempers, and help thoſe to right, who, (ſo long have ſuffered wrong, that there being no leading into Captivity, and no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in our Streets, we may once more make our boaſt of God, and ſay, Happy are the People that be in ſuch a Caſe, yea, bleſſed are the People, that have the Lord for their God.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>Printed for publick good, with hearty deſire it may be read before, (or at) all Elections.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
